National Women's Health Network records SSC.MS.00360
Sophia Smith Collection
- SERIES VIII. CONFERENCES AND MEETINGS, 1977-2011
  - Health Disparities among U.S. Women of Color: An Overview (Annual Symposium), 2002 (Box 91, Folder 13)
    - Women Taking Charge Conference
      - Contraceptive Technology: Advancing the Options, 1989 (Box 101, Folder 8)
    - Women on the Move (10th Anniversary), 1995 (Box 101, Folder 9)
    - Women's Action for New Directions (WAND): Hot Potato Project, 2004-05 (Box 101, Folder 10)
    - Women's Health Decisionmaking Program Study Group (Center for Women's Policy Studies), 1993-94 (Box 101, Folder 11)
    - Women's Health: First Annual Congress, 1998 (Box 101, Folder 12)
    - Women's Health: New Directions for the 21st Century, 1995 (Box 102, Folder 1)
    - Women's Health: The Press and Public Policy, 2005 (Box 102, Folder 2)
    - Women's Health: Progress and Future: A Symposium, 1998 (Box 102, Folder 3)
    - Women's Health Collaborative, 2000-03 (Box 102, Folder 4-9)
    - Women's Health Forum, 1980 (Box 102, Folder 10)
    - Women's Health Symposium (Kaiser Permanente), 1994 (Box 102, Folder 11)
    - Women's Health Specialists Cuban visit, 2003 (Box 102, Folder 12)
    - Women's Lens on Foreign Policy (International Women's Health Coalition), 1997 (Box 102, Folder 13)
    - Women's Progress: Perspectives on the Past, Blueprint for the Future,1998 (Box 103, Folder 1)
    - Women's Wellness Retreat (10th Annual), 1993 (Box 103, Folder 2)
    - Workshop on AIDS for Obstetrics and Gynecology Departments, 1987 (Box 103, Folder 3)
    - Writing Persuasive Health Communications: A "How to" Workshop, 1987 (Box 103, Folder 4)
    - Yale University Women's and Gender Studies Program, 2003 (Box 103, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous, 1979-2005, n. d. (Box 103, Folder 6-8)
- SERIES IX. PROJECTS, PROGRAMS, AND REFORM EFFORTS, 1963-2007
  This is the largest series and its content documents the heart of the mission of the NWHN. It contains a wide variety of materials related to thirty-four projects and programs including files of endorsements by the Network for various causes, products and people. The word "project" is used loosely and in some cases refers to a number of separate efforts within one topic. There is additional related material throughout the records especially in SERIES III. COMMITTEES, SERIES V. MEMBERSHIP AND FINANCIAL MATERIALS, SERIES VI. PUBLICATIONS AND REPORTS, SERIES VIII CONFERENCES AND MEETINGS, and SERIES XIV. SUBJECT AND REFERENCE FILES.
  The first subseries is the Black Women's Health Project. The Project was established in 1981 by Billye Avery as a two year pilot to establish links between black women and local activists in the women's health movement; educate the public about health problems of Black Americans; pressure state legislatures for increased health services for the poor; organize a major conference on Black women's health; and to bring together community projects for the poor, elderly, and rural Black Americans for improved health care. In 1983 at the Black Women's Health Conference, the BWHP became an independent national organization. It was renamed the National Black Women's Health Project in 1984 and is now the Black Women's Health Imperative. The subseries is arranged alphabetically. There is information regarding a training conference for self-help facilitators, material about and by Billye Avery, and two affiliates in California and Georgia. There is correspondence, funding material, schedules, programs and printed material related to three conferences: the Black Women's Health Conference (1983), From Cries to Whispers, Black Women and AIDS (1988), and Power of Spirituality and Healing (1988). There are budgets, financial reports and fund raising materials related to the project, as well as historical and organization materials. In 1985 two public hearings were held, one in New York City another in Los Angeles and there are testimony transcripts and organizational material related to them. Finally, there are writings and publications including three newsletters (Black Women's Health Project News, Sister Ink, and Vital Signs); a self help developers manual; and "African American Women and Abortion: 1800-1970" by Loretta Ross.
  The NWHN has made breast cancer one of its high priority issues. The Breast cancer campaign subseries contains materials related to a number of efforts by the NWHN including prevention, treatment, screening, and implant safety along files on related organizations, meetings, and media materials. This subseries is arranged alphabetically.
  In 1996 a series of public advertisements claiming a connection between breast cancer and abortion were placed in Washington metro stations. The NWHN, along with other women's health organizations, spearheaded an effort to remove the "false and misleading" announcement. In 1997 the NWHN's "Get the Facts" campaign, including an organizing kit of information, led to the removal of the ads. This material comprises the first section: Abortion and breast cancer.
  In 1979 the Network opposed the appointment of Dr. Susan Blumenthal as Senior Advisor to President Clinton on women's health. The correspondence related to this is included in this subseries because this opposition was related to a dispute over breast cancer research.
  A major project of the NWHN's has been an investigation of the relationship between breast cancer and diet. Included in this section are articles and printed material; the contents of a binder, "Breast Cancer, diet, body size and GI", a collection of research materials, abstracts, and articles on dietary fat, body mass, and the gastrointestinal tract and the relationship to breast cancer; a brochure "The Diet Your Doctor Won't Give You" from Ms. Magazine; the Network's position on recombinant bovine growth hormone in dairy cows and a possible link to breast cancer; NWHN's statement on breast cancer and diet; information regarding a dietary fat intervention trial of the Women's Health Initiative and the National Cancer Institute; and the National Cancer Institute's Women's Health Trial, a study of the relationship between dietary fat and breast cancer.
  The NWHN was part of the Breast Cancer Advocacy Communication Project, a computer training program for breast cancer activists. Correspondence, notes, and printed materials document this project as well as a report from the U.S. House Select Committee on Aging, "Breast Cancer Detection: The Need for a Federal Responses."
  In 1993 the Network produced a packet of breast cancer materials about breast cancer treatment and preventin. There is a folder of articles and printed materials of background material for the packets, one of correspondence, and the 1993 (second version) of the packet.
  The NWHN warned women about the breast cancer risks of hormones and hormone replacement therapy. The section on breast cancer and hormones contains correspondence about Breast Cancer and Estrogen by Carol Ann Rinzler, NWHN guidelines for oral contraceptive use, research by Malcolm Pike and Darcy Spicer on hormone therapy and breast cancer, materials from the National Institutes of Child Health and Human Development, NWHN media releases, and "Oral Contraceptives: Risk Factor for Breast Cancer" produced by the National Academy of Sciences, Institutes of Medicine.
  One component of the breast cancer campaign was to evaluate breast cancer screening. This section contains printed materials, correspondence, research materials, and publications related to screening as a preventative to breast cancer. Most of this material relates to mammography. There are files of advertising, articles and clippings, a publication from the NIH "Cancer facts," and regulations. In 1986 the Network created a questionnaire for the purpose of developing model clinic guidelines. The survey was sent to clinics and was designed to target problems in breast cancer screening. Individual women also reported on their experiences at clinics. There is correspondence, and there are descriptions and interview packets, responses, reports, and results from the screening project.
  The staff of the NWHN attended, sponsored and co-sponsored conferences and meetings related to breast cancer. Twelve conferences and meetings generated files of correspondence, agendas, and printed materials. The Network sponsored a Women and Cancer Conference in 1985. The reports of this conference are of particular interest.
  The NWHN has concerned itself with the safety of breast implants and advocates collections of long term data on safety and effectiveness prior to approval. To this end the Network lobbied the government, testified before congressional hearings, did media outreach, collected data, and became involved in litigation. This section includes correspondence, printed materials, government and legal documents, and press releases and media materials related to saline and silicone breast implants.
  A folder of materials documents a fundraiser featuring Rose Kushner, author and pioneering advocate for breast cancer patients, lumpectomies and breast cancer, and minorities.
  This subseries also contains correspondence, printed material, agendas and notes related to twelve organizations involved in breast cancer prevention and treatment. This section is related to the conferences and meetings section because there are workshops and conferences included in these organization files. There are substantial records from the National Action Plan on Breast Cancer, National Breast Cancer Coalition/Fund, and The National Cancer Institute. Of particular interest in the National Cancer Institute materials are articles, clippings, congressional hearings, statements on the NCI funded National Surgical Adjuvant Breast and Bowel Project research fraud where breast cancer research data was falsified over a ten year period There is a section on the risk factors of breast cancer including data and research material as well a folder on survival statistics.
  The bulk of the breast cancer campaign materials relates to tamoxifen. This section includes advertisements, articles and clippings, risk assessments, information about clinical trials, correspondence and calls from tamoxifen users, meetings, speeches and testimonies, clinical information and research materials. In 1991 the National Cancer Institute funded the Breast Cancer Prevention Trial. The trial was designed to test whether taking tamoxifen could prevent breast cancer in women who were at an increased risk of developing the disease. The trial also examined whether taking tamoxifen decreased the number of heart attacks and reduced the number of bone fractures in these women. Researchers with the National Surgical Adjuvant Breast and Bowel Project recruited participants between 1992 and 1997. Although the Network supported the use of tamoxifen as a preventative for the reoccurrence of breast cancer in certain cases, it opposed the use of the drug in healthy women and thus opposed the trial. Articles, clippings, correspondence, hearings and testimonies, meeting and research materials, protocols, media and NWHN press releases, and trial results document the Network's involvement in this issue.
  In 2001 the NWHN received funding from the California Endowment to explore the interest and feasibility of collaborating with local California groups, especially women of color, to bring them into the debate on women's health at the federal level and to working together to address women's health needs. The third subseries: The California Endowment Project contains correspondence, printed materials, feasibility studies, grant reports, and notes related to the project.
  The fourth subseries is the Cervical Cap Public Education Campaign. The Network has been committed to finding and promoting harmless methods of contraception. To this end it has promoted the use of the cervical cap. The FDA had classified the cervical cap as a "substantial risk device" and effectively prohibited its distribution. In response the NWHN provided a phone information line for consumers, lobbied the government, testified before the U.S. Senate Subcommittee on Health and Scientific Research, produced an information kit, did a media campaign, and brought legal suit. This subseries contains project information, correspondence, printed materials, legal documents, testimonies, notes, meeting agendas, lists of providers, and research materials related to the cervical cap, its distribution and promotion.
  The fifth subseries is the Network's Clearinghouse. Each year thousands of women contact the Network's Information Clearinghouse in search of accurate, relevant and reliable health information. The Clearinghouse provides evidence-based independent information from a variety of perspectives. Founded in the late 1970s, the Clearinghouse was distributing thirty-two health information packets and nine resource guides by 1986. The Clearinghouse is staffed with interns who are overseen by the Network's clearinghouse coordinator. This subseries contains correspondence, meeting reports, notes and agendas for the Clearinghouse Ad Hoc committee, information packets, copyright information for packet contents, program materials, reports, and statistics.
  The NWHN has also made consumer protection one of its high priority issues. In its first year, the NWHN organized the first ever protest against the U.S. Food and Drug Administration opposing FDA approval and lack of oversight of synthetic estrogens such as DES and high-dose estrogens in combined oral contraceptive pills. As a result Patient Packaging Inserts (PPIs) listing side effects were established for oral contraceptives-the first PPIs in U.S. history.The Consumer Protection subseries documents a number of efforts by the NWHN including drug regulation, advertising and labeling, patient education, package inserts, over the counter drugs, pharmaceutical exports, and product liability. This subseries is arranged in five sections: Consumer Product Safety Commission, FDA, over the counter drugs, product liability, and SPAN [Stop Patient Abuse Now].
  The Consumer Product Safety Commission folder consists of two reports on the accomplishments of the Commission and its reauthorization. The FDA section is the largest in this subseries and related topics can be found elsewhere in the subseries. It consists of correspondence, reports, meeting agendas, and printed materials related to twelve committees of the FDA, Consumer Exchange meetings, and a Contraceptive Efficacy Study. There is correspondence with Commissioners Jere Coyan and Donald Kennedy and between Doris Haire and the FDA on cesarean sections. The remainder of the section contains correspondence, information packets, printed materials and reports on a variety of subjects including DES, advertising, drugs and drug safety, food and drug labeling, medical device safety, medication guides, the Office of Consumer Affairs (meetings guidelines, representatives), drug exports, the NWHN opposition to FDA approval of fat substitute Olestra, over the counter drugs, patient education, package inserts, weight control products, and a Women's Health Initiative.
  The product liability section contains hearings; texts; statements; analyses of, and reports on, congressional acts and bills (Senate bills 100 and 44 and House bill 27290); a product liability statement by the NWHN; and strategy meetings. Finally there are letters and reports from Stop Patient Abuse Now related to pharmaceutical reform.
  The Dalkon Shield/IUD subseries documents the NWHN campaign against the marketing of IUDs. Although this includes devices such as the copper seven and CU380a, the subseries primarily relates to the Dalkon Shield. The A.H. Robins Company began selling the shield in 1970 and between 1970 and 1974 when it suspended marketing under pressure from the FDA, approximately 2.5 million devices were sold in the U.S. and 2 million outside the U.S. In 1975 the Network began receiving requests for information and legal help from Shield users. In response to these requests, the Network filed a worldwide class action lawsuit in 1981 against A.H. Robins requesting the recall of all devices from women worldwide. In 1983 it filed a Citizen's Petition with the FDA requesting that the Shield be declared a banned product and that notification be made that it presented an unreasonable risk to women's health. In 1984 A.H. Robins began an official recall of the Shield and in 1985 the Network filed a petition to prevent A.H. Robins from filing for bankruptcy.
  This subseries is arranged alphabetically. There are articles and clippings about IUDs and A.H. Robins, followed by attorney lists, materials related to the Network's position on attorney fees for A.H. Robins legal cases, and a chronological history of the of the Dalkon Shield. In 1985 G.D. Searle & Co. was the subject of lawsuits charging that its Copper 7 intrauterine device caused pelvic infection and infertility. There is a folder of articles, news releases, and reports regarding the device and its side effects. GynoMed began marketing another IUD, the Copper T380a, in 1988. The Network's position was one of caution because of concern that it posed the same risks as the Copper 7. There is a folder of articles as well as the Network's statement regarding the device. There is a folder of Dalkon Shield/IUD correspondence and one of financial material regarding a Dalkon Shield special appeal by the Network. Because of the international sale and distribution of the Shield, there is a section consisting of international correspondence, mailing lists, notes, and printed materials. In the legal section there are attachments, petitions, correspondence, and reports related to the Citizen's petition to the FDA; A.H. Robins materials including claims against the company; court cases against Robins, including the NWHN class action suit; and the materials regarding the motion to dismiss the Chapter 11 case. The NWHN organized a wide media and outreach project regarding the Dalkon Shield. It produced a booklet ("The Dalkon Shield"), a "Danger Sheet", a film ("IUDS Calculating the Risk"), an information packet, press releases, and statements. In addition the Network initiated a press campaign that included a press conference, radio and televisions spots, and a rally. This material is located in the Media and outreach section. The Network cooperated with a number of other organizations in their campaign against the Dalkon Shield. A number of organizations produced printed materials, correspondence, reports, and notes: Action Alert for Women, Dalkon Shield Claimants Trust, Dalkon Shield Information Network, Dalkon Shield Victims Association, the Federal Drug Administration, International Dalkon Shield Victims Education Association, Medical Claims Consultants, and the Official Committee of Dalkon Shield Claimants. Rounding out this subseries are a medical protocol for the removal of an IUD, questionnaires for IUD users, and a list of referrals for women who have sustained injuries by using the Dalkon Shield.
  Depo-Provera is the largest of the subseries. Developed in 1958 by the Upjohn Company, Depo-Provera is an artificial female hormone used as an injectable 3-month contraceptive. Studies revealed that Depo- Provera had been linked to cancers in animals, that the drug had often been used for unapproved purposes, and that fetal exposure to the drug could cause birth defects. Also the Network maintained that human studies refuting it as a cause of cancer had been flawed. The NWHN opposed the approval and marketing of the drug because it felt that the benefits did not outweigh the risks. In 1978 after various studies and committee hearings, the FDA decided that it would not approve the drug for contraceptive use. Upjohn appealed the decision. Depo-Provera also has been marketed and used overseas where there was no developed health care system to monitor its effects. The Network sent letters to third world leaders informing them of the carcinogenic effects of the drug. In 1979 the Network established a registry and encouraged women who had used Depo-Provera to supply information about their experience with the drug. The registry was used to provide statistics for testimony at FDA hearings and some of the women who participated in the registry and filled out an associated questionnaire were selected to be part of a class action lawsuit against Upjohn.
  This subseries is arranged alphabetically and contains reports; correspondence; printed material; court and legal documents including testimonies and hearing reports, petitions, and registry questionnaires. There is a report on animal studies with Depo-Provera and there are sample consent forms along with a fact sheet developed by the Network for women who request injections. The correspondence section contains letters regarding Depo-Provera lawsuits, internal NWHN memos, letters to and from members of Congress and government officials, letters from doctors, correspondence of Board member Judy Norsigian, pro Depo-Provera letters, and requests for information. There are two volumes from the Department of Health and Humans Services FDA Fertility and Material Health Drug Advisory Committee brochure on Depo-Provera and a volume of transcripts of the committee's proceedings. In addition there is "The Depo-Provera Debate," a volume of hearings before the U.S. House of Representatives Select Committee on Population.
  In 1984 an FDA panel recommended that Depo-Provera, which was approved in the U.S. only for use as a cancer palliative, should continue to be denied approval for contraceptive use. The recommendation came after a three year review of data on Depo-Provera by the FDA Public Board of Inquiry. The FDA Board of Inquiry section contains background materials, correspondence, pathology reports, prehearing conference material, correspondence and miscellaneous documents from NWHN's Counsel Steptoe & Johnson, and miscellaneous submissions to the Board. In addition there is considerable material related to the Upjohn Company's appeal including studies, submissions to the FDA, testimonies, witness communications and testimonies, transcripts of hearings, and proceedings.
  Two years later Upjohn initiated field studies in seventy foreign countries, and in 1967 the company contracted with Grady Memorial Family Planning Clinic in Atlanta, Georgia to conduct a large-scale clinical trial of 1,000 women. The Hatcher Report describes this study. There are materials from two House subcommittees. The first is a statement of the American College of Obstetrics and Gynecology on Depro-Provera use as a contraceptive before the General Oversight and Investigations Committee on Interior and Insular affairs. The second includes correspondence; articles by Stephen Minkin, a NWHN Depo-Provera consultant; and transcripts of Minkin's conversations and testimony before the House Subcommittee on International Economic Policy and Trade.